Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Are your pots and pans
and aluminum foil toxic?
Today we start by looking at the
DNA damage that may be caused
by certain uses of
aluminum cookware.
Over the last decades, the toxicity
of aluminum for humans
has been heavily discussed and
is still not completely clarified.
Those occupationally exposed
to aluminum in like smelter plants
suffer from oxidative stress, free
radicals, that can damage their DNA.
But what about just using
aluminum cookware?
Articles like this, suggesting an
unrecognized public health risk,
was limited to the developing world
where cookware is made in informal shops
by casting liquid aluminum melted
from a collection of scrap metal,
including the likes of lead batteries,
which is how you can get
so much lead leaching into peoples' food.
But then this study was published
suggesting the aluminum
itself may be harmful.
Most of our aluminum exposure comes
from processed junk that contains
aluminum-containing food additives,
including those within some processed
cheeses, baking powders, cake mixes,
frozen dough, and pancake mixes.
But approximately 20% of the daily
intake of aluminum may come
from aluminum cooking utensils,
such as pans, pots, kettles, and trays.
To see if this may be causing a problem,
they took blood from consumers
that used aluminum cookware
versus those that did not,
and found that not only were the
aluminum users walking around
with twice the level of
aluminum in their blood,
but they had more free radical damage
of their body fats and proteins.
And the total antioxidant capacity of
their bloodstream was compromised,
so, no surprise, suffered
significantly more DNA damage.
And indeed, those with the highest
levels of aluminum in their blood
tended to suffer significantly
more damage to their DNA.
No surprise, since aluminum is
considered to be a pro-oxidant agent.
These folks weren't just casually
using aluminum pots, though,
but specifically using them daily
to cook and store acidic foods,
like yogurt and tomato sauce, which
can leach out more aluminum.
But even just a week using like camping
dishes, which tend to be aluminum
since it's so light, if you were
incorporating something acidic,
like marinating a fresh catch in
lemon juice, could greatly exceed
the tolerable weekly intake
guidelines, especially for children.
Once in a while is not going to make much
of a difference, but this suggests that
you may not want to be cooking
in aluminum day-in and day-out.
What about aluminum drinking bottles?
They're nice and light but children
drinking two cups of tea or juice
a day from them could exceed the
tolerable aluminum exposure limit.
So out of an abundance of
caution, safety authorities,
like the German Federal Institute
for Risk Assessment,
recommend that consumers avoid
the use of aluminum pots or dishes
for acidic or salted foodstuffs such
as apple sauce, rhubarb, tomato puree,
or salt herring to avoid any
unnecessary ingestion of aluminum.
What about aluminum foil?
It's a common culinary practice to
wrap food in aluminum foil and bake it.
The concern is that this
could potentially present
a hazardous source of
aluminum in the human diet.
When put to the test, yes, there
was leakage from the foil to the food,
but the amount was so small that it would
be more of an issue for small children
or those suffering from
diminished kidney function.
What about just wrapping of food
in foil to store in the fridge?
Only marginal increases in aluminum
are seen, unless the food is in contact
with both the foil and, at the same
time, certain other types of metal,
for example stainless steel,
which is largely iron.
And so that sets up a battery and so can lead
to tremendous food aluminum concentrations.
And finally, you know how there's
sometimes a glossy side
of aluminum foil and then a dull side?
Which would be worse?
Fish fillets were baked and grilled
both ways, wrapped in the glossy side
versus wrapped in the dull side, and
no significant difference was found.
In our next story,
we look at the best type
of pots and pans to use.
Stainless steel is an excellent option,
the metal chosen in applications where
safety and hygiene are considered
to be of the utmost importance,
such as kitchenware.
But what about studies showing
stainless steel can leach
nickel and chromium into
foods during cooking?
(That’s what keeps the iron in the
stainless steel unstained by rust.)
The leaching is really only
when they’re brand new.
Metal leaching decreases with
sequential cooking cycles
and stabilizes after the
sixth time you cook with it.
Under more common
day-to-day conditions,
the use of stainless-steel pots
is considered to be safe
even for most people who are
acutely sensitive to those metals.
A little leaching metal can be a good
thing in the case of straight iron,
like a cast iron skillet, which
can have the beneficial effect
of helping to improve iron status,
helping to potentially reduce
the incidence of iron deficiency anemia
among reproductive age
women and children.
The only caveat is that you don’t
want to be frying in cast iron.
Frying isn’t healthy regardless,
but at hot temperatures
vegetable oil can react with
the iron to create trans fats.
What about using nonstick pans?
Teflon, also known as
polytetrafluoroethylene,
is used as an inner coating
material in nonstick cookware.
Teflon’s dark history was the subject
of a recent movie called Dark Waters,
starring Mark Ruffalo
and Anne Hathaway.
Employees in DuPont’s Teflon division
started giving birth to
deformed babies before DuPont
“removed all female staff” from the unit.
Of course, they buried it all, hiding
it from regulators and the public.
Despite this significant
history of industry knowledge
about how toxic some of the
chemicals used to make Teflon were,
they were able to keep it all hidden.
But eventually they were forced to
settle for over half a billion dollars
after one of the chemicals was linked
to kidney and testicular cancers,
pregnancy-induced hypertension,
ulcerative colitis, and high cholesterol.
“At normal cooking temperatures,
[Teflon]-coated cookware releases
various gases and chemicals that
present mild to severe toxicity.”
You’ve heard of canaries in a coal mine?
They're more like canaries in the kitchen,
as cooking with Teflon cookware is well
known to kill pet birds in the house;
or Teflon coated heat lamp bulbs
wiping out half a chicken flock.
“Apart from the gases released
during heating the cooking pans,
the coating itself starts
damaging after a certain period.
It's normally advised to use slow heating
when cooking in Teflon-coated pans,”
but you can imagine how
consumers might ignore that.
And some of the Teflon can start
chipping off if you’re not careful
and make its way into the food, though
the effects of ingestion are unknown.
This is the only study I could
find looking at the potential
human health effects of cooking
with nonstick pots and pans,
and the use of non-stick
cookware was associated with
about a 50 percent increased
risk of colorectal cancer.
But that may be because
of what they were cooking.
Non-stick cookware is used in
hazardous high-heat cooking methods,
like broiling, frying, grilling,
or barbecuing, mainly for meat,
poultry or fish, in which
carcinogenic heterocyclic amines
are formed from the animal protein.
And then the animal fat can
produce another class of carcinogens
called polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
Though it’s possible it
was the Teflon itself,
which contains suspected carcinogens
like that C8 compound from the movie,
also known as PFOA,
perfluorooctanoic acid.
“Due to toxicity concerns,
this chemical has been replaced
with other chemicals such as
GenX, but these new alternatives
are also suspected to
have similar toxicity.”
But we’ve already so contaminated the
Earth with it that we now can get it
prepackaged in food before it’s
even cooked, particularly in fish,
dairy products, and meat,
which is now the main source
of human exposure to
these toxic pollutants.
Of those, seafood is the worst.
In a study of diets from around the world,
fish and seafood were major contributors
of the perfluoroalkyl substances,
as expected, given that everything
eventually flows into the sea.
Though the aquatic food chain
is the primary transfer mechanism
for these toxins into the human
diet, “food stored or prepared
in greaseproof packaging
materials,” like microwave popcorn,
may also be a source.
And in 2019, Oral-B Glide
dental floss was tested.
6 out of 18 dental floss products
they tested showed evidence
of Teflon-type compounds.
So, did those who used
those kinds of floss
end up with higher levels
in their blood stream?
Yes, apparently so.
Higher levels of
perfluorohexanesulfonic acid
were found in Oral-B Glide flossers.
There’s lots of environmental
exposures in the modern world
we can’t avoid, but we
shouldn’t be making things worse
by adding it to consumer products.
But hey, at least it gives
us some power to lower
our personal exposure to
these harmful chemicals.
Finally today,
we look at the role that aluminum may
play in causing Alzheimer’s disease.
The so-called
"aluminum hypothesis"
for the cause
of Alzheimer's disease
dates back to 1965,
when the inadvertent
injection of aluminum
into the brains of rabbits
caused neurological symptoms
along with what initially
looked like Alzheimer's disease
tangles in the brain.
Then, in the 1970s,
it was first reported
that the aluminum content
of Alzheimer's brains
was higher than that
of control brains on autopsy.
Following that, there was
a rash of fatal dementia cases
attributed to dialysis fluids
contaminated with aluminum.
This trio of findings
led researchers
to suggest that aluminum,
the third most
abundant element on Earth
(after oxygen and silicon),
may play a role
in the development
of Alzheimer's disease.
The first crack in the theory
was the realization that,
upon closer inspection,
the tangle-like changes
in rabbit brains
were not much like those
found in human
Alzheimer's disease after all.
The changes in aluminum-induced
dialysis encephalopathy
were also dissimilar.
Aluminum could certainly
be toxic to the brain,
but not necessarily in a way
that had anything to do
with Alzheimer's disease.
And, subsequent autopsy studies
of Alzheimer's victims
did not consistently find
higher aluminum levels,
and even if they did,
elevations in brain aluminum
could be a consequence
rather than a cause
(reflecting
Alzheimer's disease damage
to the blood brain barrier).
The aluminum hypothesis
came under heavy fire
in the scientific community.
Only later did we learn
that the most vocal critics
were secretly-paid
aluminum industry hacks.
In hindsight,
that was probably unnecessary,
as the tide of evidence
eventually turned against
the role of aluminum.
What convinced me
was a meta-analysis
that failed to find a connection
between regular antacid use
and Alzheimer's.
Processed foods
contain a variety
of aluminum-containing
additives,
such as anti-caking agents
in pancake mix,
melting agents
in American cheese,
meat binders, gravy thickeners,
rising agents
in some baking powders,
and dye binders in candy.
However,
over-the-counter antacids
are probably
the most important source
for human aluminum exposure
in terms of dose.
In terms of the safety
of dietary aluminum,
the tolerable weekly intake
is 1 mg per healthy kilogram
of body weight.
So, if you weigh
about 150 pounds (67.5 kg),
you shouldn't get more than,
like, 10 milligrams a day.
One day of Maalox
can give you
38 hundred milligrams,
nearly 400 times
the daily safety limit,
and nowhere on the label
does it say
not to take
with acidic beverages,
such as fruit juice.
Washing an antacid down
with orange juice
can increase
aluminum absorption eight-fold.
The total aluminum intake
in drinking water
and processed foods
in most countries may only
be a few milligrams a day.
But, some antacids can increase
daily aluminum consumption
by up to several grams,
a thousand-fold higher.
And so, if antacid use
isn't related
to Alzheimer's risk,
then ingested aluminum
is unlikely to be a cause.
Now, just because aluminum
doesn't cause Alzheimer's
doesn't mean aluminum intake
is necessarily benign.
Those who cook with aluminum
and store acidic foods,
like yogurt and tomato,
in aluminum cookware
suffer significantly more
DNA damage,
leading some regulators
to recommend consumers
avoid the use
of aluminum pots or dishes
for acidic or salted foodstuffs.
In my video on antiperspirants
and breast cancer,
I note how the FDA
and European safety authorities
specifically advise against
using aluminum antiperspirants
on damaged skin,
which may even include
avoiding them after shaving.
As a "metalloestrogen,"
aluminum absorption may explain
why breast cancer may occur
as much as twenty years earlier
in women using antiperspirant
and shaving their armpits
more than three times a week.
You can also avoid
high dietary sources
by choosing non-aluminum
baking powder for baking
and avoiding
processed cheese.
Aluminum salts can give cheese
"desirable slicing properties,"
but that means a single
grilled cheese sandwich
can end up exceeding
the World Health Organization's
provisional tolerable
daily intake of aluminum
by as much as 400 percent.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.